<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-homenet-arch PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-homenet-arch.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.behringer-autonomic-network-framework PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.behringer-autonomic-network-framework.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7030 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7030.xml">
]>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-sarikaya-t2trg-sbootstrapping-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IoT Bootstrapping Analysis">Secure IoT Bootstrapping: A Survey</title>

    <author fullname="Behcet Sarikaya" initials="B.S." surname="Sarikaya">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5340 Legacy Dr. Building 3</street>
          <street/>
          <city>Plano</city>
          <region>TX</region>
          <code>75024</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yizhou Li" initials="Y.L." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue</street>
          <city>Nanjing</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>210012</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohit Sethi" initials="M.S." surname="Sethi">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>02420</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author fullname="Robert Cragie" initials="R.C." surname="Cragie">
      <organization>ARM</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>110 Fulbourn Road</street>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>CB1 9NJ</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document presents a survey of secure bootstrapping mechanisms available for smart objects that are part of an Internet of Things (IoT) network. It aims to provide a structured classification of the available mechanisms. The document does not prescribe any one secure bootstrapping mechanism and rather presents IoT developers with different options to choose from, depending on their use-case, security requirements and the user interface available on their smart objects.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>An Internet of Things (IoT) network is composed of connected things that cooperate together to accomplish tasks such as smart buildings, smart environment monitoring system, and intelligent transport systems. The size of an IoT network varies from a couple of devices to tens of thousands depending on the application. A smart object, or a things, or a device in an IoT network is typically produced by a variety of vendors and they are normally heterogeneous in terms of the constraints on their power supply, communication capability, computation capacity and memory available.</t>

      <t>Before classifying and describing the various methods of bootstrapping, it is important define what is meant by the term security bootstrapping. There have been several varying definitions that have been used in different drafts and research papers. For the purpose of this document, we define Security bootstrapping as follows: "it is the process by which a thing/device/smart object in an IoT network securely becomes operational at a given location and point of time." This definition is broad on purpose since the term IoT itself represents a very diverse spectrum of application scenarios. So for example, pairing of phones over bluetooth to exchange files, and securely connecting IEEE 802.15.4 sensors in a factory to the backend both require some form of secure bootstrapping to become operational. Secure bootstrapping must result in either delivery or generation of some keying material for secure operation. This is different form simply joining a network with DHCP to communicate.</t>

      <t>It is also important to note that a device which simply connects to a service or entity using certificates and TLS/DTLS is not considered as bootstrapping and rather authentication. This no different than using your laptop browser and connecting to an online service over HTTPS. For the purpose of this draft, the focus is on secure bootstrapping rather than secure authentication.</t>

      <t>While some bootstrapping approaches are more user-intensive and require extensive user-involvement by scanning QR codes or entering passwords; others maybe more automated, such as those that rely on mobile networks <xref target="I-D.sethi-gba-constrained"/>.</t>


    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Analysis of available mechanisms">
      <t>We classify available bootstrapping solutions into the following three major categories:</t>
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Managed/Centralized/AAA: These mechanisms rely on a centralized node or server for bootstrapping the IoT devices. There is generally an implicit assumption that the devices being bootstrapped have some connectivity to the server or node that is responsible for bootstrapping the device.</t>
        <t>P2P/Adhoc: These mechanisms are traditionally used for establishing secure communication between two devices for ad-hoc communication, such as pairing two smart phones. These methods do not rely on centralized server for bootstrapping.</t>
        <t>Miscellaneous: These methods rely on some components from both centralized and P2P mechanisms. For example, they may use Public-keys and certificates but instead of relying on a centralized server, the devices being bootstrapped might simply exchange their public-key over an out-of-band channel to then derive share-secrets for further secure communication.  </t>
      </list></t>

      <section title="Managed/Centralized">
        <t>This section provides some examples of centralized methods. </t>
           <t>Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) is an authentication framework that supports multiple authentication methods. EAP is designed for use in network access authentication and typically runs directly over data link layers without IP. Several EAP methods have been standardized for different purposes.  One widely used method is the EAP-TLS <xref target="RFC7250"/> which enables mutual authentication and distribute keying material to secure subsequent communications. However it only supports certificate-based mutual authentication, thus public key infrastructure is required. The ZigBee Alliance has specified an IPv6 stack aimed at IEEE 802.15.4 
          devices mainly used in smart meters developed primarily for SEP 2.0
          (Smart Energy Profile) application layer traffic <xref
          target="SEP2.0"/>. For secure bootstrapping, ZigBee IP uses EAP-TLS.</t>

          <t>EAP-PSK <xref target="RFC4764"/> is another EAP method. It
          realizes mutual authentication and session key derivation using a
          Pre-Shared Key (PSK). Normally four messages are exchanged in the
          authentication process. Once the authentication is successful,
          EAP-PSK provides a protected communication channel.</t>

           <t>EAP-IKEv2 <xref target="RFC5106"/> is an EAP method based on
          IKEv2. It provides mutual authentication and session key
          establishment between an EAP peer and an EAP server. It supports
          authentication techniques that are based on different credentials
          including asymmetric key pairs, symmetric keys and passwords.
          Besides, it is possible to use a different authentication credential
          in each direction. For example, the EAP server authenticates itself
          using public/private key pair and the EAP peer using symmetric key.
          As a result different combinations of credentials are expected to be
          used in practice. Compared with EAP-TLS and EAP-PSK, EAP-IKEv2
          supports mobility and different authentication techniques.</t>

          <t> Generic Bootstrapping Architecture (GBA) is another bootstrapping method that falls in centralized category. GBA is part of the 3GPP standard [3gppts33220] and is based on 3GPP Authentication and Key Agreement (3GPP AKA).  GBA is an application independent mechanism to provide a client application (running on the User equipment (UE)) and any application server with a shared session secret.  This shared session secret can subsequently be used to authenticate and protect the communication between the client application and the application server. GBA authentication is based on the permanent secret shared between the UE's Universal Integrated Circuit Card (UICC), for example SIM card, and the corresponding profile information stored within the cellular network operator's Home Subscriber System (HSS) database. <xref target="I-D.sethi-gba-constrained"/> describes a resource-constrained implementation of GBA for IoT applications.</t>

          <t>Open Mobile Alliance (OMA) Light-weight M2M standard also defines secure bootstrapping for resource-constrained IoT devices with a centralized Bootstrapping Server (BS). The current standard defines the following four bootstrapping modes:</t>
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Factory Bootstrap: An IoT device in this case is configured with all the necessary bootstrap information during manufacturing and prior to its deployment.</t>
              <t>Bootstrap from Smartcard: An IoT device retrieves and processes all the necessary bootstrap data from a Smartcard.</t>
              <t>Client Initiated Bootstrap: This mode provides a mechanism for an IoT client device to retrieve the bootstrap information from a Bootstrap Server. This requires the client device to have an account at the Bootstrap Server and credentials to obtain the necessary information securely.</t>
              <t>Server Initiated Bootstrap: In this bootstrapping mode, the bootstrapping server configures all the bootstrap information on the IoT device without receiving a request from the client. This means that the bootstrap server needs to know if a client IoT Device is ready for bootstrapping before it can be configured. For example, a network may inform the bootstrap server of a new connecting IoT client device.</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t> The Kerberos protocol <xref target="RFC4120"/> is a network authentication protocol that allows several endpoints to communicate over an insecure network. Kerberos relies on a symmetric cryptography scheme and requires a trusted third party, that guarantees the identities of the various actors. It relies on the use of "tickets" for nodes to prove identity to one another in a secure manner. There has been research work on using Kereberos for IoT devices<xref target="kerberosiot"/>.</t>

          <t>ANIMA bootstrapping: TBD</t>

           
          
    </section>
      
     <section title="P2P/Adhoc">
     <t>
     	P2P or adhoc methods are used for bootstrapping typically for creating local associations. These local associations may later be used for connecting an IoT device to a centralized server. These bootstrapping mechanisms typically rely on an out-of-band (OOB) channel in order to prevent man-in-the-middle (MitM) attacks. Contextual and location-dependent information on the OOB channel is assumed to be secret from anyone not present at the location where the bootstrapping takes place.Based on how the OOB channel is used, the P2P methods can be further classified into two sub categories:
     </t>
        	  <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Key derivation: Contextual information received over the OOB channel is used for shared key derivation. For example, <xref target="proximate"/> relies on the common radio environment of the devices being paired to derive the shared secret which would then be used for secure communication.</t>
          <t>Key confirmation: A Diffie-Hellman key exchange occurs over the insecure network and the established key is authenticate with the help of the OOB channel. For example, Bluetooth simple pairing <xref target="SimplePairing"/> use the OOB channel to ask the user to compare pins and approve the completed exchange. </t>
       </list></t>

       <t>P2P/Adhoc methods might use a discrete OOB channel, such as Bluetooth simple pairing that relies on pin codes. Alternatively these secure bootstrapping methods might rely on noisy sensory inputs such as audio. These protocols have to cope with a fuzzy secret, i.e. noisy secret input that differs between the devices being bootstrapped.</t>
    </section>


    <section title="Miscellaneous">
      <t>As stated earlier, some secure bootstrapping methods rely on components from both adhoc and centralized categories. We discuss some examples in this section. </t>
     
      

      <t><xref target="I-D.kumar-6lo-selective-bootstrap"/> presents a
      selective bootstrapping/commissioning method by introducing the
      concept of Commissioning Tool (CT). In this method the devices are
      let to connect to the network and execute 6LowPAN neighbor discovery
      protocol and have an IPv6 address before they are authenticated.
      Then the devices are selected one by one in some order to
      communicate with the CT via untrusted constructed route. Once the ID
      of joining device is authenticated, CT sends the layer-2 key
      material to the device via secured channel, which is established by
      DTLS by exchanging credential material installed during
      manufacturing.</t>

      <t>Raw Public Key</t>
          <t>
          <xref target="RFC7250"/> defines how raw public keys can be used to authenticate constrained devices or in mutual authentication using EAP-TLS or DTLS. Raw public key TLS/DTLS extension simplifies client_certificate_type
   and server_certificate_type to carry only SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure with the raw public key instead of many other parameters found in the
   certificates. The device and the authentication server (AS) exchange client_hello and server_hello messages and send their raw public keys. The device and AS validate the keys by comparing the pre-configured values <xref target="I-D.sarikaya-6lo-bootstrapping-solution"/>.
          </t><t>
          
               </t><t>
               Raw public key approach when used with DTLS offers a simple secure bootstrapping solution especially for smart energy and building automation applications. It can be easily integrated with the Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP) where there is already a CoAP server which can also be the authentication server.
               
                    </t><t>
                    
                    </t>
          
    </section>
</section>

 <section title="Discussion">
      <t>It is evident that there are many different methods of secure bootstrapping available. The choice on of the method is constrained by the type of device being bootstrapped. Depending on the link-layer technology used, and the User Interface (UI) available, one or more of the above mentioned categories might be suitable. In this section we discuss some general guidelines that would help in selecting the right bootstrapping method.

        TBD</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The whole draft deals with security considerations.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>TBD</t>
  </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4944'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4120'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3561'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4728'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3626'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7252'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4919'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5216'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5487'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6345'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6550'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6786'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7251'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7228'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7250'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7400'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4764'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5106'?>

      <reference anchor="SimplePairing">
        <front>
          <title>Simple pairing whitepaper</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Bluetooth, SIG</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2007" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name=" Technical report" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE802.15.4"
                 target="http://standards.ieee.org/findstds/standard/802.15.4-2011.html">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Std. 802.15.4-2011</title>

          <author fullname="" surname="IEEE Standard">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

       <reference anchor="kerberosiot"
                 target="https://kit.mit.edu/sites/default/files/documents/Kerberos_Internet_of%20Things.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Kerberos for Internet-of-Things</title>

          <author fullname="Thomas Hardjono" surname="Hardjono">
            <organization>MIT Kerberos and Internet Trust Consortium</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="proximate">
        <front>
          <title>Proximate: proximity-based secure pairing using ambient wireless signals.</title>

          <author fullname="Suhas Mathur" surname="Mathur">
            <organization>AT&amp;T Security Research Center, New York</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Robert Miller" surname="Miller">
            <organization>WINLAB, Rutgers University, North Brunswick</organization>
          </author>

           <author fullname="Alexander Varshavsky" surname="Varshavsky">
            <organization>AT&amp;T Labs, Florham Park, NJ</organization>
          </author>

           <author fullname="Wade Trappe" surname="Trappe">
            <organization>WINLAB, Rutgers University, North Brunswick</organization>
          </author>

           <author fullname="Narayan Mandayam" surname="Mandayam">
            <organization>WINLAB, Rutgers University, North Brunswick</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE802.1x"
                 target="http://standards.ieee.org/getieee802/download/802.1X-2010.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.1X Port-Based Network Access Control</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IEEE Std 802.1X-2010</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="5" month="February" year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE802.15.9"
                 target="http://grouper.ieee.org/groups/802/15/private/members_area.html">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Draft Recommended Practice for transport of key
          management protocol (KMP) datagrams</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IEEE P802.15.9/D01</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SEP2.0"
                 target="hhttp://www.zigbee.org/non-menu-pages/zigbee-ip-download/">
        <front>
          <title>ZigBee IP Specification</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ZigBee Alliance</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.pritikin-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.struik-6tisch-security-considerations'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.sarikaya-6lo-bootstrapping-solution'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.oflynn-core-bootstrapping'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.garcia-core-security'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.nikander-esp-beet-mode'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.kwatsen-netconf-zerotouch'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.he-iot-security-bootstrapping'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.kumar-6lo-selective-bootstrap'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.sethi-gba-constrained'?>

       <reference anchor="MIT2014">
        <front>
          <title>Physical Unclonable Functions and Applications: A Tutorial</title>

          <author initials="C." surname="Herder">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="F.K." surname="Farinaz Koushanfar">
		  </author>
		 <author initials="S.D." surname="Srinivas Devadas">
		  </author>
          <date year="2014" month="August" />
        </front>
		<seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the IEEE" value=""/>
		<seriesInfo name="vol." value="102"/>
		<seriesInfo name="no." value="8"/>
		<seriesInfo name="pp." value="1126-1141"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

